A Guide to the Papers of Henry S. Spaulding, 1859-1865 (bulk 1861-1865)
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Henry S. Spaulding 1859-1865 (bulk 1861-1865)
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
38-156
This collection consists of 43 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased by the library on 18 January 1938.
Biographical/Historical Information
Henry S. Spaulding, Captain, 38th New Jersey Volunteers and Lawrence Clinton, Spaulding's brother-in-law, 12th Pennsylvania Regiment.
Scope and Content
The papers contain letters, 1861-1865, of soldiers in the Army of the Potomac, chiefly of Henry S. Spaulding, concerning military service in Virginia, specifically, mustering and training, camp life, bounties, commissions, battles near Fredericksburg, Va., and Richmond, Va., Burnside's expedition to North Carolina (1862). There are comments on General McClellan and Grant, African American troops, strategy of the Army of the Potomac, the capture of deserters and Confederate soldiers.
The letters also discuss issues of low morale, friendly fire incidents, reinlistment, disciplinary problems, an engagement, 1862, near Yorktown, Va., and officers' opinions of the poems written by Spaulding's wife, Anna "Birdie" Spaulding.
Spaulding's letters, 1863-1865, to his daughters concern a scouting party and an artist taking pictures on the battlefield.
Spaulding's incomplete diary, 20 April 1865 to 14 May 1865, kept at Fort Powhatan, Va., comments on Lincoln's death, African American troops, Confederate soldiers, his wife's poems, and politics.
There are also instructions, concerning guard duty and court martials; and a pass, 1862.
The collection also contains letters, 1861-1863, from Lawrence Clinton to his sister Anna Spaulding, concerning army advances, seeking a commission, and his failing health. A letter, 1865, from Helen Hawley to Anna Spaulding conveys family news and her desire to see Jefferson Davis executed.
An earlier letter, 1859, concerns the purchase of barrel staves.
Contents List
- W. F. Jewett & Co. to F. W. O'Brion 1859 August 29
  re: Barrel Stave Purchases
- Edwin Frye to Sister 1861 November 5
  re: Encampment on Washington, D. C.
- [Addin Young] to Aunts [1861] November 10
  re: Journey to Washington encampment
- Charles Frye to Sister 1862 February 8
  re: Battle "Missouri", Burnside Expedition, recruitment at home
- Charles Young to Aunts 1862 March 6
  re: Camp Casey, Va. Quarters (description); officers; desire to be in battle at Richmond
- Issac Frye to Daughter 1862 April 24
  Detailed description of Engagement near Yorktown, with personal thoughts and reactions
- Issac Frye to Daughter 1862 May 4
  Detailed description of bombardment of Yorktown Camp, with personal thoughts and reactions
- Issac Frye to Daughter 1862 May 25
  re: Hardships at camp near "Kidder's Mills"
- Henry [Spaulding] to "Birdie" [his wife] 1862 September 14
  re: Mustering and training at Camp [Caldwalleder]; bounties
- Henry [Spaulding] to "Birdie" [his wife] 1862 September 15
  re: "Legal advice" for Mr. Buskirk's son; Mustering; News of McClellan and Stonewall Jackson in Maryland
- Walter [Rounds] to "Cousin" 1862 October 9
  re: Camp at [Munsons Hill], Va. Description of battlefields; Desire to fight the "Damd Traitors"
- Lawrence to Sister 1863 March 22
  re: Vacancy in Penna. Regiment, aid of Henry; failing health
- H. S. Spaulding to Allie and Gallie [his daughters] From Camp Robertson, near Falmouth; 1863 March 22
  re: General appearance around Frdericksburg, Va.; artist taking pictures on battlefield; George Washington; Father's home
- Henry [Spaulding] to "Birdie" from Camp Robertson near Falmouth, Va. Detailed description of battle near Fredericksburg. Comments on poor strategy of Army of Potomac 1863 May 9
- Henry S. Spaulding (Captain of 38th Co. New Jersey Volunteers) [1864 November]
  "Instructions for the Guards of the Fort"
- J. Johnson (Brig. General) "General Orders No. 3" 1864 November 8
  re: results of courts-martial
- Henry S. Spaulding (Captain) "General Orders No. 8" 1864 November 9
  re: results of courts-martial at Fort Powhatan, Va.
- Henry S. Spaulding to "Birdie [his wife] from Fort Powhatan, Va. 1864 November 23
  re: Food; family problems
- Henry S. Saulding to E.G. Smith, Lieut. at Fort Powhatan, Va. 1864 November 26
  re: instructions to men of the company
- "Papa" [Henry Spaulding] to "Lillie Pet" (his daughter) for Fort Powhatan, Va. 1865 January 7
  re: Amusing account of scouting party in search of Orderly Sergeant Cooper Wiltsey
- Henry Spaulding to 1st Lieut. A. E. Hand at Fort Powhatan, Va. 1865 January 31
- Henry Spaulding to Lieut. E.G. Smith 1865 March 25
  re: Disciplinary problems: Firing upon Provost Marshall by "Colored Cavalry"
- Diary of [Henry Spaulding] approximately 1865
  40 pages